<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Renan LE CARO</title>
    <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io" />
    <updated>2020-05-28T13:17:30+10:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Ciboulette.net : produces email marketing </title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/ciboulettenet-a-web-platform-for-vegetable-farmers.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/ciboulettenet-a-web-platform-for-vegetable-farmers.html</id>
            <category term="Programming"/>

        <updated>2020-05-28T11:33:19+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    It all started about 7 years ago. My mother got laid off and had to find a job. She already had a large garden and decided to make a living selling vegetables. She invested little capital as the activity was supposed to last only a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>It all started about 7 years ago. </p>
<p>My mother got laid off and had to find a job. She already had a large garden and decided to <strong>make a living selling vegetables</strong>. She invested little capital as the activity was supposed to last only a few years until retirement. </p>
<p>Therefore the production was small. Like, very small. She <strong>tried selling at the local market</strong> but you need large volumes to make the trip worth it. Clients always leave the last vegetables left in each box, they don't want to take the last few tomatoes. Turns out, those tomatoes were just the only ones she had at first.</p>
<p>So she decided to try another sales channel : <strong>she would sell vegetables by email</strong>. Each week, she'd send a list of all the produces that were available in the garden. The clients (mostly friends and acquaintances at first) were free to order by simply replying to the email with what they wanted. At the end of the week, she'd prepare each order and clients would come to the farm to pick up their order. They would pay directly on location.</p>
<p>Preparing orders for clients is <strong>a lot of extra work</strong>, taking orders is also quite a process, and the whole thing was a bit inefficient, but she did manage to sell vegetables. </p>
<p>I was a student at the time at university and needed a project for a university class. With a few friends we decided to start a project that'd <strong>automate most of the process</strong> of offering products and taking orders.</p>
<p>The business model was to create a great app for my mother, and sell it to other farmers later on as a SAAS.</p>
<p>The first iteration was based on AngularJS, mongo, express. It was hosted on heroku. The second iteration was based on <strong>meteor</strong> with everything real time. This is the <strong>version that's still running today</strong>.</p>
<p>The project has been running for many years. The farmer's contribution (14.90€/month) pays for the server, but with only 8 users the app is <strong>barely generating a tiny profit</strong>. I could, in theory, get a lot more users, the response to my cold calls was excellent.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But this project taught me something : being responsible for a professional tool that can crash at any moment is no fun.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The risk of the app crashing, the emails ending in spam, the reminder SMSs failing, etc .. is quite high, and the impact is that farmers can end up blocked in their work, and lose sales. </p>
<p>Today, i tend to <strong>prefer creating completely free side projects</strong>, because it stresses me less to have a program crash if said program is free to use. It's also forcing me to create very lean applications that tend to be <strong>frontend only</strong>. Therefore, they can be hosted for free indefinitely. </p>
<p>I'm still interested in the SAAS model, but I now keep in mind that <strong>being on call 24/7 limits you freedom</strong>. I live in Russia now, and would love to spend two weeks in the Trans-Siberian. But that's mean spending two weeks doing support from a train in the middle of nowhere. That's a no-go.   </p>
<p>So, next time, I'll think a bit more before creating a product people will rely on. </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The FEFU Campus</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/the-fefu-campus.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/the-fefu-campus.html</id>
            <category term="Photography"/>

        <updated>2020-05-27T23:35:29+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is really just an excuse to try displaying a few photos in Publii
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is really just an excuse to try displaying a few photos in Publii</p>
<div class="gallery gallery-wrapper--wide"   >
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3034-1.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3034-1-thumbnail.jpg" alt="The bridge to the island" width="720" height="478"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3026-1.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3026-1-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Reflections of the campus in the sea" width="720" height="720"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3048.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3048-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Campus building, they were lit by two different light sources, but I accentuated that quite a bit" width="720" height="478"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3042.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3042-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Construction site for the new university buildings" width="720" height="720"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3024.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3024-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Another view of the bridge" width="720" height="720"></a></figure>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Giving Publii a try </title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/giving-publii-a-try.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/giving-publii-a-try.html</id>
            <category term="Programming"/>

        <updated>2020-05-28T10:51:29+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    As a web developer, I've created some websites for family and friends. My default tool for that was WordPress, because you could easily set them up, pick a theme, mess with the CSS a bit and let them write the content. But hosting a wordpress&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>As a web developer, I've created some websites for family and friends. My default tool for that was WordPress, because you could easily set them up, pick a theme, mess with the CSS a bit and let them write the content.</p>
<p>But hosting a wordpress website is always a trade-off between reliability and costs. On one side you have free hosts giving you a terrible VM that can barely handle the administration side, on the other overpriced plans for what's really a tiny website with usually almost no traffic. </p>
<blockquote>
<p>I've always thought that WordPress was using a tank to kill a fly.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So until now, for non technical business owners, I've set up a free host and the administration of the website was usually quite slow and unreliable. If the client wanted something more reliable, I'd get a paid hosting plan, but that would include some overhead for me. </p>
<p>For my personal projects I personally used custom made static websites, with or without automatic generation. But I didn't see myself explaining the details of git push, markdown and CLI use to my parents. I thought I should work on an ideal, user friendly static website editor one of those days.  </p>
<p>Today i discovered <a href="https://getpublii.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Publii</a> and thought i'd give it a try for my blog. If it's satisfactory, I might recommend it to my less tech-savvy friends in the future. Until now I've been pleasantly surprised. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Minimage : minimal image editor</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/minimage-minimal-image-editor.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/minimage-minimal-image-editor.html</id>
            <category term="Programming"/>

        <updated>2020-05-27T23:35:16+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This was one of my first project with the main focus on page size and bundle size. After learning a bit more about Webpack at virtualQ, i wanted to see how small a modern we app could be. The main problem I was trying to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This was one of my first project with the main focus on page size and bundle size. After learning a bit more about Webpack at virtualQ, i wanted to see how small a modern we app could be.</p>
<p>The main problem I was trying to solve was a personal one : I wanted to annotate a screenshot of an app to a friend before sending it to him. All i needed was to draw an arrow on a small picture. I couldn't find an app that would only do that, so I created one using the technology I knew best : front end javascript.</p>
<p><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/minimage/">The app</a> is far from perfect, but it runs quite smoothly on a variety of platforms.  </p>
<p>The app is freely accessible and open source but I haven't really worked on promoting it. Since then i've bought a new phone and don't really need as much to save space on the internal memory. I rarely make use of minimage but keep it online, just in case it might be useful one day.  </p>
<p> </p>
<p><img class="post__image align-center" src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/3/minimage-2.png" alt="Screenshot of minimage" width="565" height="321"></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
