<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Renan LE CARO</title>
    <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io" />
    <updated>2020-08-04T16:42:13+10:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Life in Владивосток</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/life-in-vladivostok.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/life-in-vladivostok.html</id>
            <category term="Life"/>

        <updated>2020-08-04T12:28:04+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I've been living in Vladivostok, Russia, since the end of February 2020. I'm a student here, learning the Russian language. I'm a bit older than the average student but my life is still very student-like anyway. I really enjoy the energy of younger friends and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I've been living in Vladivostok, Russia, since the end of February 2020. </p>
<p>I'm a student here, learning the Russian language. I'm a bit older than the average student but my life is still very student-like anyway. I really enjoy the energy of younger friends and the large amount of free time we have.</p>
<h2>Life is cheap </h2>
<p>I'm renting a room on the DVFU campus, it costs barely 40€/month, but it's only possible to rent it as a student, the study itself costing around 140€/month. As a student, I can benefit from the very cheap student health insurance that costs about 50€/year. </p>
<p>Overall, I'm spending less than 500€/month here to live quite comfortably. I'm happy to have found this opportunity. </p>
<h2>Life is good</h2>
<p>The Russian class starts at 10am every day. It lasts 2 hours, and is currently happening via Skype. That means I don't have to spend 3 hours in transport every day. When the confinement will be over though, we'll have to go back to physical classes, that happen in the city. Traffic is usually quite bad in the morning, and the trip without traffic from the FEFU campus to the city is about 1 hour without traffic, so it's not unusual to have to spend one hour thirty in transports to go to class. I really hope we'll have the option to keep our classes online, I find it way more convenient. </p>
<p>We live near the sea and near nature, it's great. We've done countless barbecues, trekking trips and swimming sessions. </p>
<p>The only scholarly thing I'm required to do to keep my student status is to be present in class. Doing the homework is recommended, but kind of optional. I don't do them anymore so that I can focus all my energy on the programming of <a href="https://ciboulette.net">ciboulette.net</a>  </p>
<h2>This too, shall pass</h2>
<p>I won't stay eternally here, my motivation to learn Russian is lower than when I arrived, and my fascination for the country is now back to simple curiosity. </p>
<p>I'll head back to Europe in December, to focus on the sales process of ciboulette. I'm thinking about moving to France first, to help my sister for a while with her setup in a new house. I'll do calling and development work when I have free time, and keep an eye on my niece at the same time. </p>
<p>Then, my currently favored plan is to set myself up in Odessa, Ukraine, to enjoy the good weather, Russian speaking opportunities and affordable cost of living. French citizen get 6 months visa free there, which should be enough for me to know if I want to stay here longer or not. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Automating local backups of DO MUP on Ubuntu</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/automating-backups-of-digital-ocean-meteor-up-install-to-your-ubuntu-workstation.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/automating-backups-of-digital-ocean-meteor-up-install-to-your-ubuntu-workstation.html</id>
            <category term="Code"/>

        <updated>2020-08-04T11:58:07+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    DO + MUP = 💙I've migrated my main project, https://ciboulette.net, from Heroku to digital ocean, with the help of the awesome meteor up tool that's still actively maintained. I wanted a way to automate the backups of production to my own computer. In meteor, the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2>DO + MUP = 💙</h2>
<p>I've migrated my main project, <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/">https://ciboulette.net</a>, from Heroku to <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/">digital ocean</a>, with the help of the awesome <a href="https://meteor-up.com/">meteor up</a> tool that's still actively maintained.</p>
<p>I wanted a way to automate the backups of production to my own computer. In meteor, the only thing really worth backing up is the content of the mongoDB.</p>
<p><strong>We need two things : a script</strong> that does the backup, <strong>and a cron job</strong> to run regularly</p>
<h2>Backup script</h2>
<p>You just need to configure the two environment variables at the top (in bold)</p>
<p><strong>daily_backup.sh</strong></p>
<pre>#!/bin/sh<br><br># folder where to store the last 7 daily backups, without trailing slash<br>DUMPFOLDER="<strong>/home/renan/cl/app/dump</strong>"<br><br># IP of your digital ocean droplet<br>DO_INSTANCE_IP="<strong>46.101.232.182</strong>"<br><br># so that notifications know on which display to show when called from the cron tab<br>export DISPLAY=:0<br><br># Let it quit when it crash<br>set -e<br><br>DUMPFILE="$DUMPFOLDER/daily_$(date +"%y-%m-%d").backup.gzip"<br><br>if [ ! -f $DUMPFILE ];<br>then<br>  continue<br>else<br>  echo "Already done today" &amp;&amp; exit 0<br>fi<br><br>notify-send "Backing up ..."<br><br># ssh to the instance, then ask the mongodb container to output an archive of all dbs, then stream that back to your machine. <br>ssh "root@$DO_INSTANCE_IP" "docker exec mongodb mongodump --archive --gzip" &gt; "${DUMPFILE}"<br><br># Only keep the last 7 dumps <br>ls -tp $DUMPFOLDER/ | grep -v '/$' | tail -n +8 | xargs -I {} rm -- $DUMPFOLDER/{}<br><br>notify-send "... backup done."</pre>
<p>Make sure the script is executable with <code>chmod +x daily_backup.sh</code></p>
<h2>CRON setup</h2>
<p>We will run this script every hour. The first time it runs it will do the backup, and the next time it will see the file exists already and just exit. The next day the filename will be different and therefore a new backup will be run. </p>
<p>Open the cron editor : <code>crontab -e</code> </p>
<p>Add the following line, modifying the path in bold to point to your script.  </p>
<p><code>1 * * * * /<strong>home/renan/cl/app/.production/daily_backup.sh</strong> &gt;/dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1</code></p>
<p>This will run the script every hour when minutes are equal to 1, so if you start your computer at 8:30 it will first run at 9:01</p>
<p>The redirect after the command are to avoid having errors show up in the logs. Ubuntu is a bit confused when cron jobs generate outputs.  </p>
<h2>How to restore such backup</h2>
<p>Having backup is nice, but knowing out to restore them is better. </p>
<pre>#!/bin/sh<br><br># folder with the dumps<br>DUMPFOLDER="<strong>/home/renan/cl/app/dump</strong>"<br># IP of your digital ocean droplet<br>DO_INSTANCE_IP="<strong>46.101.232.182</strong>"<br><br># Let it quit when it crash<br>set -e<br><br># find the latest backup file<br>LATEST_FILE=$(ls -t1 "$DUMPFOLDER/" |  head -n 1)<br>LATEST_DUMP="$DUMPFOLDER/$LATEST_FILE"<br>echo "Restoring to production from $LATEST_DUMP"<br>read -p "Press enter to continue .."<br><br># pipe file to the mongorestore inside the mongodb docker container inside the droplet <br>cat "${LATEST_DUMP}" | ssh "root@$DO_INSTANCE_IP" "cat | docker exec -i mongodb mongorestore --archive --gzip --drop"</pre>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Mermaid Gdocs</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/mermaid-gdocs.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/mermaid-gdocs.html</id>
            <category term="Code"/>

        <updated>2020-06-05T08:55:28+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Working at virtualQ, it happened a few times that I'd start a project with unclear requirements, then presented it to the rest of the team just to see everything needing to be changed or canceled. To avoid such disappointing outcome, I tried to make more&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Working at virtualQ, it happened a few times that I'd start a project with unclear requirements, then presented it to the rest of the team just to see everything needing to be changed or canceled. </p>
<p>To avoid such disappointing outcome, I tried to make more design docs. A design doc is roughly said a document that will detail all the possible solutions to a problem, and serve as a support for debate, ideas and discussions. After a design doc is accepted by the team, you can go ahead with the development with less risk of requirements being inadequate. </p>
<p>Most features would include some back end and front end elements, and some user flows. Trying to make the documents more readable, I added as many sequence diagrams as possible. Sequence diagrams are excellent at communicating a process. Their layout forces you to be succinct  as there's not much space for walls of texts and unnecessary details.</p>
<p>I first edited the diagrams in the excellent <a href="https://www.websequencediagrams.com/">websequencediagrams.com</a> and pasted a screenshot in the google documents, but that was a bit of a pain to maintain. This tool keeps a copy of the source code, so i'd just need to edit it and update the resulting picture in the google document, but no one else had access to said source code. I thought i could just save the source code in the image description field in google docs, to make it easier to update the diagram for anyone in the team.</p>
<p>This is when I realized i could use this "trick" to create a <a href="https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/mermaid/636321283856?pann=cwsdp&amp;hl=en">google docs add-on</a>. In a classic case of "putting off writing documentation by focusing on the tools used in documenting", I followed the (super confusing) tutorials on the google documentation website for G Suite add-ons. </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/8/Screenshot-from-2020-06-05-08-52-21.png" alt="Screenshot of the mermaid add-on in the g-suite marketplace" width="989" height="731">
<figcaption >The mermaid add-on listed in the g-suite marketplace </figcaption>
</figure>
<p> </p>
<p>The project has evolved a bit with time but stays relatively simple in terms of code. It has gathered quite a lot of users (10K) despite me not putting any efforts in marketing it. I guess we have a product-market fit here, but no business plan at all. This is really just a few lines of JavaScript to make the power of the mermaid JS library available in google docs. I don't think it makes sense to charge for it, and it costs nothing to keep it running. </p>
<p>I've made it open source, with the code hosted on github, feel free to have a look there : <a href="https://github.com/renanlecaro/mermaid-gdocs">https://github.com/renanlecaro/mermaid-gdocs</a></p>
<p><a href="https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/mermaid/636321283856?pann=cwsdp&amp;hl=en"> The mermaid add-on listed in the g-suite marketplace </a></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Documenting systems</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/documenting-systems.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/documenting-systems.html</id>
            <category term="Code"/>

        <updated>2020-05-30T11:00:13+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Back when I was working at virtualQ, I had to do some documentation. At first I didn't quite enjoy it, feeling like this was a chore. But documenting a system can be a very interesting task. I also had to explain our systems to new&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Back when I was working at virtualQ, I had to do some documentation. At first I didn't quite enjoy it, feeling like this was a chore. But <strong>documenting a system can be a very interesting task</strong>. I also had to explain our systems to new hires after we raised some funds and quickly grew the team. </p>
<p>We had a <strong>documentation website for our API</strong>, based on markdown. It was very technical, with manually copy pasted sample API responses. It wasn't very visual. It had endpoints documented publicly while they were only for internal use. It had a lot of outdated content, and felt more like a patchwork of data bits than a comprehensible thing.</p>
<p>My fist step was to <strong>remove the documentation off irrelevant endpoints</strong>. The docs were kind of an hybrid between a public api documentation and some internal guide for new hires. I made dedicated to customers trying to use our api only.</p>
<p>It still had a<strong> "wall of text" feeling though</strong>. To make it more palatable, I tried to add visuals. Integrating <a href="https://mermaidjs.github.io/">mermaid</a> to the docs was quite easy, I styled it roughly with some css rules. <strong>Sequence diagrams are awesome</strong>. I used them to communicate the different workflow we had and some typical scenarios the clients would like to use our API for. </p>
<p>We had a <strong>complex state machine</strong> that tracks the state of a caller through our system. I tried to <strong>represent it as a graph</strong>, but that was a bit too cluttered, so i split it in two graphs and removed some of the transitions that were not normally happening. </p>
<p>Finally, I wanted to fix our <strong>outdated sample API requests and responses</strong>. Our API was evolving rapidly and having outdated samples was more confusing than helpful. I created a <strong>tiny script that curl commands and update the API answer samples</strong> with them. I had to do some dirty grepping on the answers to replace dates, ids, etc .. to avoid polluting the git log with meaningless edits every time we'd refresh the samples.</p>
<p>We deployed the new version of the documentation. Some of our new hires still had some use for the old version (that documented more endpoints) so we added a link to it. <strong>We don't have any tracking on the docs website</strong>, so I have no idea what the readership is, but it was great as a learning experience.</p>
<p>It made me love mermaidJS so much, that I eventually ended up building a <a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/mermaid-gdocs/">google docs addon</a> for it. </p>
<p>I like the idea of <strong>writing tutorials as markdown, with E2E test instructions mixed in</strong>, and outputting the result (text, screenshots, response samples) as a document. It would guarantee that the tutorials stay in sync with the product and don't become outdated, with always fresh screenshots. It would make the task of writing E2E tests for some web app a dual purpose task, where you'd <strong>generate both a helpful document and some smoke tests</strong> in one go. </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Ciboulette.net : produces email marketing </title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/ciboulettenet-a-web-platform-for-vegetable-farmers.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/ciboulettenet-a-web-platform-for-vegetable-farmers.html</id>
            <category term="Code"/>

        <updated>2020-05-30T10:34:03+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    It all started about 7 years ago. My mother got laid off and had to find a job. She already had a large garden and decided to make a living selling vegetables. She invested little capital as the activity was supposed to last only a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>It all started about 7 years ago. </p>
<p>My mother got laid off and had to find a job. She already had a large garden and decided to <strong>make a living selling vegetables</strong>. She invested little capital as the activity was supposed to last only a few years until retirement. </p>
<p>Therefore the production was small. Like, very small. She <strong>tried selling at the local market</strong> but you need large volumes to make the trip worth it. Clients always leave the last vegetables left in each box, they don't want to take the last few tomatoes. Turns out, those tomatoes were just the only ones she had at first.</p>
<p>So she decided to try another sales channel : <strong>she would sell vegetables by email</strong>. Each week, she'd send a list of all the produces that were available in the garden. The clients (mostly friends and acquaintances at first) were free to order by simply replying to the email with what they wanted. At the end of the week, she'd prepare each order and clients would come to the farm to pick up their order. They would pay directly on location.</p>
<p>Preparing orders for clients is <strong>a lot of extra work</strong>, taking orders is also quite a process, and the whole thing was a bit inefficient, but she did manage to sell vegetables. </p>
<p>I was a student at the time at university and needed a project for a university class. With a few friends we decided to start a project that'd <strong>automate most of the process</strong> of offering products and taking orders.</p>
<p>The business model was to create a great app for my mother, and sell it to other farmers later on as a SAAS.</p>
<p>The first iteration was based on AngularJS, mongo, express. It was hosted on heroku. The second iteration was based on <strong>meteor</strong> with everything real time. This is the <strong>version that's still running today</strong>.</p>
<p>The project has been running for many years. The farmer's contribution (14.90€/month) pays for the server, but with only 8 users the app is <strong>barely generating a tiny profit</strong>. I could, in theory, get a lot more users, the response to my cold calls was excellent.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But this project taught me something : being responsible for a professional tool that can crash at any moment is no fun.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The risk of the app crashing, the emails ending in spam, the reminder SMSs failing, etc .. is quite high, and the impact is that farmers can end up blocked in their work, and lose sales. </p>
<p>Today, i tend to <strong>prefer creating completely free side projects</strong>, because it stresses me less to have a program crash if said program is free to use. It's also forcing me to create very lean applications that tend to be <strong>frontend only</strong>. Therefore, they can be hosted for free indefinitely. </p>
<p>I'm still interested in the SAAS model, but I now keep in mind that <strong>being on call 24/7 limits you freedom</strong>. I live in Russia now, and would love to spend two weeks in the Trans-Siberian. But that's mean spending two weeks doing support from a train in the middle of nowhere. That's a no-go.   </p>
<p>So, next time, I'll think a bit more before creating a product people will rely on. </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The FEFU Campus</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/the-fefu-campus.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/the-fefu-campus.html</id>
            <category term="Life"/>

        <updated>2020-05-27T23:35:29+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is really just an excuse to try displaying a few photos in Publii
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is really just an excuse to try displaying a few photos in Publii</p>
<div class="gallery gallery-wrapper--wide"   >
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3034-1.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3034-1-thumbnail.jpg" alt="The bridge to the island" width="720" height="478"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3026-1.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3026-1-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Reflections of the campus in the sea" width="720" height="720"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3048.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3048-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Campus building, they were lit by two different light sources, but I accentuated that quite a bit" width="720" height="478"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3042.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3042-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Construction site for the new university buildings" width="720" height="720"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3024.jpg" ><img src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/5/gallery/DSC_3024-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Another view of the bridge" width="720" height="720"></a></figure>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Giving Publii a try </title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/giving-publii-a-try.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/giving-publii-a-try.html</id>
            <category term="Code"/>

        <updated>2020-05-28T10:51:29+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    As a web developer, I've created some websites for family and friends. My default tool for that was WordPress, because you could easily set them up, pick a theme, mess with the CSS a bit and let them write the content. But hosting a wordpress&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>As a web developer, I've created some websites for family and friends. My default tool for that was WordPress, because you could easily set them up, pick a theme, mess with the CSS a bit and let them write the content.</p>
<p>But hosting a wordpress website is always a trade-off between reliability and costs. On one side you have free hosts giving you a terrible VM that can barely handle the administration side, on the other overpriced plans for what's really a tiny website with usually almost no traffic. </p>
<blockquote>
<p>I've always thought that WordPress was using a tank to kill a fly.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So until now, for non technical business owners, I've set up a free host and the administration of the website was usually quite slow and unreliable. If the client wanted something more reliable, I'd get a paid hosting plan, but that would include some overhead for me. </p>
<p>For my personal projects I personally used custom made static websites, with or without automatic generation. But I didn't see myself explaining the details of git push, markdown and CLI use to my parents. I thought I should work on an ideal, user friendly static website editor one of those days.  </p>
<p>Today i discovered <a href="https://getpublii.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Publii</a> and thought i'd give it a try for my blog. If it's satisfactory, I might recommend it to my less tech-savvy friends in the future. Until now I've been pleasantly surprised. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Minimage : minimal image editor</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/minimage-minimal-image-editor.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/minimage-minimal-image-editor.html</id>
            <category term="Code"/>

        <updated>2020-05-27T23:35:16+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This was one of my first project with the main focus on page size and bundle size. After learning a bit more about Webpack at virtualQ, i wanted to see how small a modern we app could be. The main problem I was trying to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This was one of my first project with the main focus on page size and bundle size. After learning a bit more about Webpack at virtualQ, i wanted to see how small a modern we app could be.</p>
<p>The main problem I was trying to solve was a personal one : I wanted to annotate a screenshot of an app to a friend before sending it to him. All i needed was to draw an arrow on a small picture. I couldn't find an app that would only do that, so I created one using the technology I knew best : front end javascript.</p>
<p><a href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/minimage/">The app</a> is far from perfect, but it runs quite smoothly on a variety of platforms.  </p>
<p>The app is freely accessible and open source but I haven't really worked on promoting it. Since then i've bought a new phone and don't really need as much to save space on the internal memory. I rarely make use of minimage but keep it online, just in case it might be useful one day.  </p>
<p> </p>
<p><img class="post__image align-center" src="https://renanlecaro.github.io/media/posts/3/minimage-2.png" alt="Screenshot of minimage" width="565" height="321"></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
