<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Renan LE CARO</title>
    <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io" />
    <updated>2020-05-27T22:58:09+10:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Giving Publii a try </title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/giving-publii-a-try.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/giving-publii-a-try.html</id>
            <category term="Blog"/>

        <updated>2020-05-27T22:49:46+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I've always thought that WordPress was using a tank to kill a fly. The surface area for attacks was too large, the admin could barely run most of the time, and the large amount of plugins was mostly a way to keep the marketing guys&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I've always thought that WordPress was using a tank to kill a fly.</p>
<p>The surface area for attacks was too large, the admin could barely run most of the time, and the large amount of plugins was mostly a way to keep the marketing guys happy, and not a way to just make a more user friendly website.</p>
<p>As a dev, I've created some websites for family and friends. My default tool for that was WordPress, because you could easily set them up, pick a theme, mess with the CSS a bit and let them write the content.</p>
<p>I personally used a custom made static site, with or without automatic generation, for my personal project's presentation pages. But I didn't see myself explaining the details of git push, markdown and CLI use to my parents. </p>
<p>Today i discovered Publii and thought i'd give it a try for my blog. If it's satisfactory, I might recommend it to my less tech-savy friends in the future. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Minimage : minimal image editor</title>
        <author>
            <name>Renan LE CARO</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://renanlecaro.github.io/minimage-minimal-image-editor.html"/>
        <id>https://renanlecaro.github.io/minimage-minimal-image-editor.html</id>
            <category term="Webpack"/>
            <category term="Project"/>
            <category term="Open source"/>
            <category term="JS"/>
            <category term="Canvas"/>

        <updated>2020-05-27T22:42:26+10:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This was one of my first project with the main focus on page size and bundle size. After learning a bit more about Webpack at virtualQ, i wanted to see how small a modern we app could be. The main problem I was trying to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This was one of my first project with the main focus on page size and bundle size. After learning a bit more about Webpack at virtualQ, i wanted to see how small a modern we app could be.</p>
<p>The main problem I was trying to solve was a personal one : I wanted to annotate a screenshot of an app to a friend before sending it to him. All i needed was to draw an arrow on a small picture. I couldn't find an app that would only do that, so I created one using the technology I knew best : front end javascript.</p>
<p>The app is far from optimized, but it runs quite smoothly on a variety of platforms.  </p>
<p>The app is freely accessible and open source but I haven't really worked on promoting it. Since then i've bought a new phone and don't really need as much to save space on the internal memory. I rarely make use of minimage but keep it online, just in case it might be useful one day.  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
